Guide to the Coleman Dowell Papers 1925-1985 MSS 036
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Coleman Dowell Papers
1925-1993
MSS 036
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
32.0 linear feet (31 boxes)
(Robert) Coleman Dowell (1925-1985) was a composer, lyricist, poet, playwright, novelist, and critic. He corresponded with many famous authors and well-known personalities from the early 1960's through 1984. The collection includes correspondence, original sheet music composed by Dowell for television and Broadway musicals during his early years in New York City, photographs, and manuscripts of published and unpublished novels, poetry, short fiction, and plays.
Provenance
The Coleman Dowell Papers were donated by Dr. Bertram Slaff, M.D., to the Fales Library at New York University in December 1986. Mr. Frank Walker, Head of Special Collections, acted as liaison between the Archives and Dr. Slaff and arranged for the collection's delivery to the Fales Library.
In 2008, Dr. Slaff donated an additional 1.5 linear feet of materials, notated hereafter as "Accretion 2008."
Biographical Note
(Robert) Coleman Dowell was born to Mordon and Beulah Dowell in Adairville, Kentucky on May 29, 1925. Dowell attended several country schools, among them, a one room schoolhouse where Latin and Greek were taught. His last two years of high school were at Simpson County High in Franklin, a new county school where he was on the school paper. Dowell served in the U.S. Army, Medical Corps from 1944-45 and as an assistant to the prosecution in war crimes trials in Manila in 1945-46. He was eventually promoted to the rank of sergeant. During this period he also attended the University of the Philippines. Dowell returned home to the U.S. in 1946 and settled in Louisville for a few years where he was a full-time member of the National Guard. Here, he wrote the musical play that brought him to New York
Dowell moved to New York City in 1950, initially finding work as a model for automobile and airline ads and as a typist. From 1950-53 Dowell was employed as a song writer and lyricist for the Dumont television show, Once Upon a Tune, which starred Bea Arthur, Elaine Stritch, Alice Ghostley, and Charlotte Rae. Dowell composed nearly 1,000 works for weekly broadcast. He also worked as David Merrick's protege and with John LaTouche on the abortive Broadway musical version of Eugene O'Neill's Ah, Wilderness!. 1957 was a pivotal year for Dowell. It was in January of this year that he managed to meet Carl Van Vechten, author of The Tattooed Countess. Dowell wanted permission to attempt to adapt the piece to the musical stage. He played for Van Vechten selections from a score for The Tattooed Countess and won Van Vechten's approval for the rights. Carl Van Vechten was known to his friends as "Carlo." His career included stints as a music critic for the New York Times, as a novelist during the 1920s, and as a photographer for which he never sought nor received payment. He photographed many of the major figures in the arts world. His wife was Fania Marinoff, a retired actress. Van Vechten introduced Dowell into his circle of friends which included many celebrities: Isak Dinesen, Langston Hughes, Leontyne Price, Geoffrey Holder, Gloria Vanderbilt, Sidney Lumet, Eileen Herlie, Kim Hunter, Barbra Streisand, Dianne Carroll, Pearl Bailey, Anthony Armstrong Jones, Tallulah Bankhead, Luise Rainer, Laurence Olivier, Gertrude Stein, the Gish sisters, the Duke and Duchess of Windsor, George Kaufman, Noel Coward, and Maurice Sendak, among others.
The Tattooed Countess, which opened in 1961, was panned by the critics and closed within a few days. Dowell, who had written the book, score and lyrics, tried his luck with another theatrical experiment, Eve of the Green Grass. This play was presented at the Chelsea Art Theatre in 1965 and starred Kim Hunter. Seeing his play on the stage, Dowell concluded that the theatre was not his metier and turned his attention to writing novels. This was done without the mourning that the failure of The Tattooed Countess had induced. Dowell's early experiences in the theatre were used in two magazine articles, "At Home with Drosselmeier" and "A Handful of Anomalies" which were published in Bomb Magazine in 1984 and 1985, respectively. His theatrical career was also included in his unfinished autobiography, A Dark Book, which was published by The Dalkey Archive Press in June 1993 under the title: A Star-bright Lie.
Dowell had found only disillusionment in the theater. He decided to seek his fortune as a writer of fiction. Dowell had already experienced some success in writing fiction. His short story, "Alter Frau im Garten" had been published in 1962. Over a fifteen year period Dowell wrote five novels: One of the Children is Crying (1968), Mrs. October was Here (1974), Island People (1976), Too Much Flesh and Jabez (1977), and White on Black on White (1983). Remarkably, the first four novels had been written concurrently. These novels were intricate both in concept and in form. It was during this period that Dowell enjoyed the critical praise and friendship of such noted authors as Walter Abish, Thom Gunn, John Hawkes, Ann Lauterbach, Gilbert Sorrentino, Maurice Sendak, Edmund White, and Tennessee Williams.
Dowell was talented and he yearned to be famous. He very much needed a popular readership. One of the Children is Crying, one of his most accessible books, was widely reviewed, with reviews appearing in Boston, Denver, Hollywood, Houston, Louisville, Milwaukee, Sacramento, and Tulsa. Since One of the Children is Crying had been published earlier in England under the title, The Grass Dies, reviews also appeared in England and Ireland. Surprisingly, reviews for Dowell's second novel, Mrs. October was Here, were meager and from rather obscure sources. Nevertheless, this novel was always mentioned as being Dowell's favorite. Island People was a favorite with critics and other authors, and was called Dowell's masterpiece. Supporters of this novel included Tennessee Williams, Gilbert Sorrentino, Ihab Hassan, and Walter Abish, but reviews were still not as plentiful as had been the case with his first novel. The New York Times called it "a work of art" and brought Dowell some national attention. Too Much Flesh and Jabez was the least reviewed of Dowell's novels. The New York Times, nevertheless, called it "a tour de force." White on Black on White received many, but mixed, reviews. Dowell was given a tribute before the publication of his last novel in the Fall 1982 issue of The Review of Contemporary Fiction. This issue, called the Paul Bowles-Coleman Dowell number, contains the major critical articles on Dowell which had appeared up to this date.
Three different journals published nearly all of Dowell's short fiction. New Directions: An Anthology of Prose and Poetry published the following titles: "The Keepsake" (#26, 1973), "The Birthmark" (#27, 1973), "I Envy You Your Adventure" (#28, 1974), "First Person Biography" (#29, 1974), "Victor: (#30, 1975), "If Beggars were Horses" (#31, 1975), "Singing in the Clump" (#32, 1976), "The Moon, the Owl, my Sister" (#33, 1976), "Ham's Gift" (#35, 1977), and "My Father was a River" (#36, 1978). The English quarterly, Ambit, published the following titles: "I am the Beast" (#61, 1975), "The Drought Ends" (#65, 1976), "Her Good Man Gone" (#69, 1977), "A Lifetime Proposition" (#73, 1978), "Patridge House" (#76, 1978), "The Snake House" (#79, 1979), "The Silver Swanne" (#89, 1980), "Person Waiting" (#94, 1983), and "Kitty" (#100, 1985). Conjunctions published "The Great Godalmighty Bird" (#4, 1983), "Eve of the Green Grass" (novel excerpt) (#6, 1984), and "Writings on a Cave Wall" (#8, 1985). As has been already stated, "Old Woman in a Garden" or "Alte Frau im Garten" (translation by Ruth Landskoff-Yorck) was published in Frankfurter Hefte in 1962. "Handy" appeared in Kentucky Renaissance in 1976, and "The Hobo" appeared in ADENA in Spring 1986. During 1983 both Conjunctions and Grenfell Press republished "The Silver Swanne" which Conjunctions editor, Bradford Morrow, in "Postscript," The Houses of Children: Collected Stories (1987) termed Dowell's greatest work of short fiction. It should also be noted that Dowell reviewed books for the Courier-Journal of Louisville, Kentucky from 1978-1985.
Dowell received critical praise from the leading authors and critics of his day. He never received the popular support he so desperately needed. His later years were plagued by ill health. Although there were good times, Dowell could not escape feelings of disillusionment, suicide, or as he put it, "the balcony beckons me." In the early morning hours on Saturday August 3, 1985, Dowell leapt from his 15th floor apartment balcony overlooking Fifth Avenue. As is the case with so many other writers or artists, the attention focused on Coleman Dowell accelerated after his death. In 1987, The Houses of Children: Collected Stories was published by Weidenfeld and Nicholson and this publishing company also reissued One of the Children is Crying. Too Much Flesh and Jabez was also made available via the Dalkey Archive Press.
Three major works by Dowell were left unfinished. These include Eve of the Green Grass, a novel; Dowell's autobiography entitled, A Dark Book and his private journal 1968-1984 which is a running diary of his life, writings, attitude towards people, and also includes personal observations for stories. Two excerpts from A Dark Book had been published earlier in Bomb magazine under the titles: "At Home with Drosselmeier" (#10, Fall 1984) and "A Handful of Anomalies" (#13, Fall 1985). These deal with Dowell's early adventures in New York City and his relationship with Carl Van Vechten, as well as his early theatrical career.
Dowell was given a final tribute at his apartment on November 3, 1985. A large number of famous personalities representing the worlds of dance, art, literature, music, theater, and education toasted their friend and praised his accomplishments as a gifted composer, poet, playwright, novelist, and critic.
Sources:
The Coleman Dowell Papers, (New York: Fales Library, NYU, 1993)
Contemporary Authors, (Detroit: Gale Research, 1990)
Kuehl, L., & J. Kuehl, eds. (1989). Prospectus for a start-bright lie: Coleman Dowell's Theatrical Memoirs (NY: The Review of Contemporary Fiction 7:3 Fall 1987)
Scope and Content Note
The Coleman Dowell Papers includes correspondence, musical scores and lyrics, photographs, and ephemera, as well as the texts of three major unfinished works: a novel, a private journal, and an autobiography. The latter, which Dowell had entitled A Dark Book, was published in 1993 as A Star-Bright Lie. The 2008 Accretion includes all of the above, as well as an audio recording of Dowell singing some of his songs. The accretion also contains various materials related to the publication of A Star-Bright Lie, as well Bertrand Slaff's attempts to publish Dowell's journals.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Published and Unpublished Works
Series III: Musical Works and Lyrics
Series IV: Works by Others and Miscellaneous Materials
Series V: Media
Although the greatest concentration of correspondence is found in Series I, correspondence is interfiled throughout the Papers.
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Published and Unpublished Works
Series III: Musical Works and Lyrics
Series IV: Works by Other and Miscellaneous Materials
Series V: Media
Miscellaneous Oversize
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Abish, Cecile; Abish, Walter; Adams, Frances; Aman, Madeleine; Arnold, Kenneth; Baker, Roger; Bax, Martin; Beeson, Jack, 1921-; Beeson, Nora; Collins, Jack; Dignan, Josef; Dowell, Coleman; Dunphy, Jack; Fey, Isabella; Ford, Ruth, 1915-; Geva, Tamara; Greene, Harlan; Griffin, John Howard, 1920-1980; Gunn, Thom; Halliday, Mark; Herlie, Eileen; Hunter, Kim, 1922-2002; Inge, William; Kent, Louise Andrews, 1886-1969; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Kuehl, John Richard, 1928-; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997; Lauterbach, Ann, 1942-; Low, Betty; Lyndon, Andrew; Morrow, Bradford, 1951-; O'Brien, John, 1879-1952; Pais, Lila; Purcell, John; Purdy, James; Segal, Lore Gorszmann; Sendak, Maurice; Sessoms, Hella; Slaff, Bertram; Sorrentino, Gilbert; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964; Van Vechten, Fani Marinoff; White, Delilah, 1903-; White, Edmund, 1940-; Whitmore, George, 1945-1989; Williams, Shirley; Wilson, Morris; American drama |y 20th century.; American literature |y 20th century.; Authors, American |x Correspondence.; Composers, American.; Drawings.; Galley proofs.; Paintings (visual works); Scripts (documents); Typescripts.
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I: Correspondence, consists of correspondence between Dowell and many famous authors and well-known personalities dating from the early 1960s through 1984, for example, Maurice Sendak, Gilbert Sorrentino, Carl Van Vechten, and Edmund White.
  Offsite boxes & barcodes
  Box 1 - Barcode: 31142042236557 Box 2 - Barcode: 31142042236565 Box 3 - Barcode: 31142042236573
  - A n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abish, Walter and Cecile: 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adams, Frances: 1967, 1974, 1978, 1979, 1985, n.d., 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aman, Madeleine: 1967, 1978, 1985, 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arnold, Kenneth: 1976, 1977, 1978, 1981, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B: 1951, 1952, 1974, 1978, 1981, 1983, 1984, n.d., 1951-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baker, Roger: 1963, 1969, 1984, 1963-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bax, Martin: 1974, 1979, 1982, 1985, n.d., 1974-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beeson, Jack and Nora: 1959, 1973, 1976, 1959-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Boston University [Gotlieb, Howard] 1969, 1974, 1986, 1969-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - C - D: 1974, 1978-1982, 1984, 1985, n.d., 1974-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Collins, Jack: 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dignan, Josef n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dowell, Coleman [to Collins, Jack]: 1983, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dowell, Coleman [to Hella and others] 1968, 1971, 1972, 1974, 1976, 1978, 1980-1984, 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dunphy, Jack: 1968-1972, 1974, 1976, 1978, 1984, 1968-1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - E - F: 1954, 1959, 1961-1963, 1965, 1968, 1972, 1976, 1984, 1954-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Family [Dowell, Mrs. M.W.]: 1951, 1965, 1967, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Family [Dowell, Ron (nephew)]: 1974, 1976, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Family [Misc.]: 1953-1955, 1962, 1963, 1967, 1968, 1974, 1984, 1953-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Family [Wohlken, James & Gayle]: 1966, 1967, 1971, 1981-1984, 1966-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Family [Wohlken, Jeremy & Shane]: 1982, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fey, Isabella: 1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ford, Ruth: 1963, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - G - K: 1957, 1959, 1960, 1962, 1964, 1967, 1971, 1974-1976, 1978, 1981, 1983, 1985, 1957-1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Geva, Tamara: 1966, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Greene, Harlan: 1984 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Griffin, John Howard: 1962, 1967, 1969, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gunn, Thom: 1980, 1982, 1983, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Halliday, Mark [correspondence and ms.]: 1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Herlie, Eileen: 1959, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hunter, Kim: 1967, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Inge, William: 1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Kent, Louise Andrews: 1956, 1967, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Kentucky Education Association: 1980, 1983, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Koch, Ed: 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kuehl, John [to and from]: 1976-1980, 1982-1984, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - L: 1961, 1962, 1965, 1982, n.d., 1961-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Laughlin, James: 1972 - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lauterbach, Ann [includes ms.]: 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Low, Betty: 1979, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lyndon, Andrew: 1963, 1967, 1971, 1973, n.d., 1963-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Readers: 1961, 1965, 1968, 1974, 1975, 1977-1982, 1984, 1986, n.d., 1961-1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - M: 1953, 1955, 1965, 1975-1980, 1982, 1985 Morrow, Brad, 1953-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - [see Brad Morrow, Series IV, Box 1:1], undated (Box 2)
  - N - R: 1959, 1960, 1962, 1977, 1979, 1983, 1984, 1959-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - O'Brien, John: 1982, 1983, 1985, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pais, Lila: 1957, 1965, 1968, 1970, n.d. Purcell, John, 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - [see White, Edmund, Series I, Box 3:16], undated (Box 2)
  - Purdy, James: 1963, 1965, 1967, 1974, n.d., 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - S: 1965, 1966, 1973, 1974, 1985, 1965-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Segal, Lore & mother (Franzi Groszmann): 1971, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sendak, Maurice [see also Map Case]: 1968-1973, 1975, 1976, 1978, 1981, 1982, n.d., 1968-1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sessoms, Hella: 1969-1972, 1982-1985, 1969-1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Slaff, Bertram: 1980-1983, n.d., 1957, 1963-1968, 1971, 1974, 1976, 1978, 1957-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sussler, Betsy: 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert: 1976, 1978, 1980-1984, 1976-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - T: 1961, 1964, 1968, 1978, 1984, 1985, 1961-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tam's Death: July 13 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified: 1946, 1950, 1957, 1968, 1970, 1972, 1976, 1980, 1982, 1984, 1946-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified n.d. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Van Vechten, Carl: 1957, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Van Vechten, Carl: 1959 - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Van Vechten, Carl: Photos & postcards: 1957-1961, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Van Vechten, Fania Marinoff: 1959, 1960, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - W - Z: 1954, 1962, 1963, 1966, 1974, 1979, 1983, 1954-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - White, Delilah [see White, Edmund, Series I, Box 3:16], undated (Box 3)
  - White, Edmund: 1976, 1978, 1980-1985, n.d., 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Whitmore, George: 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Williams, Shirley n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Wilson, Morris: 1975, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Writer [A.S. Burack, ed.]: 1967, 1968, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series II: Published and Unpublished Works
  Scope and Content note
  Series II: Published and Unpublished Works, contains reviews pertaining to Dowell's published works, and some correspondence, mostly from friends or admirers regarding a particular novel, short story, etc. This series is divided into two subseries: Subseries A: Novels and Short Stories; and Subseries B: Plays and Dramatic Writings. The bulk of Dowell's published works is novels; unpublished material consists of plays, poems, and miscellaneous writings. Much of the materials in Subseries B are copies of Dowell's published novels or plays which he used as research material for other projects. The series also contains The Great Godalmighty Bird- a long, unpublished play with songs, personal correspondence, lists of scenes for the plays and themes, and short two- or three-character plays.
  Series II, Subseries A: Box 1 - Barcode: 31142042236581 Box 2 - Barcode: 31142042236599 Box 3 - Barcode: 31142042236607 Box 4 - Barcode: 31142042236615 Box 5 - Barcode: 31142042236623 Box 6 - Barcode: 31142042236631 Box 7 - Barcode: 31142042236649 Box 8 - Barcode: 31142042236656 Box 9 - Barcode: 31142042236664 Box 10 - Barcode: 31142042236672 Box 11 - Barcode: 31142042236680 Box 12 - Barcode: 31142042236698 Box 13 - Barcode: 31142042236706
  Series II, Subseries B: Box 1 - Barcode: 31142042236714 Box 2 - Barcode: 31142042236722
  - Subseries A: Novels, Short Stories and Other Writings
    (1949 - 1986)
    - Cancer: 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - City Sundays: 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Great Godalmighty Bird: 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ham's Gift: 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ham's Gift [German translation] n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - I Envy You Your Great Adventure: 1966-68, 1974, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - If Beggars Were Horses: 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - In The Mood: [1966-68], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The Moon, The Owl, My Sister: 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - My Father was a River: 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Silver Swanne: 1979, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Silver Swanne: [notes] [ca. 1979] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Kid's Brother [later, Wool Tea]: 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Writings as Yet Unfound in a Kentucky Cave n.d. [later, Writings on a Cave Wall 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - One of the Children is Crying/The Grass Dies. [British ms.]: ca. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - One of the Children is Crying/The Grass Dies. [carbon ms.]: ca. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - One of the Children is Crying/The Grass Dies [clippings]: 1967, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Grass Dies [correspondence]: 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - One of the Children is Crying [correspondence]: 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - One of the Children is Crying [correspondence]: 1968-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - One of the Children is Crying [corrected ts, p 1-126]: ca. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - One of the Children is Crying [corrected ts, p 126-230]: ca. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - One of the Children is Crying [Reviews] 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - One of the Children is Crying [Title page, ad card & quote page] n.d., undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mrs October Was Here [ts. carbon]: ca. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mrs October Was Here [ts. annotated]: ca. 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mrs October Was Here [notes and fragments]: n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Mrs October Was Here [early version]: n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Mrs. October Was Here [miscellaneous]: n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Mrs. October Was Here [miscellaneous]: n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Mrs. October Was Here [miscellaneous]: n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Mrs October Was Here [miscellaneous; clippings]: 1973, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Mrs October Was Here [correspondence]: 1970-1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Island People [Ian]: ca. 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Island People [The Keepsake]: 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Island People [The Surgeon]: ca. 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Island People [Webster's story (1)]: 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Island People [Webster's story (2)]: 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Island People [Webster's story (3)]: 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Island People [fragments] n.d., undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Island People [fragments] n.d., undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Island People [correspondence]: 1973, 1975, 1976, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Island People [clippings]: 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Island People [Up At Claudo's] n.d., undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Island People [1]: ca. 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Island People [2]: ca. 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Island People [3]: ca. 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Island People [scrapbook]: 1976, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Too Much Flesh and Jabez [notes and fragments]: 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Too Much Flesh and Jabez [Edmund White's notations]: 1977 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Too Much Flesh and Jabez [correspondence]: 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Too Much Flesh and Jabez [clippings]: 1977, 1978, 1981, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - White on Black on White [original ms. p. 1-135]: ca. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - White on Black on White [original ms. p. 136-252]: ca. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - White on Black on White [ms. p. 1-141]: ca. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - White on Black on White [ms. p. 142-283]: ca. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - White on Black [notes and fragments] ca. 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - White on Black on White [contract and correspondence]: 1982, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - White on Black on White [correspondence]: 1983, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - White on Black on White [clippings]: 1983, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 8)